Donald Trump is one of the most overtly
activist presidents in American history.
He takes positions on major issues that
many of us might deem to be
unprecedented or even extreme. And he
does that on purpose. He wants to shake
up the status quo. He wants to keep his
domestic political opponents and even
foreign leaders on their heels. And he's
serious when he says America first. It's
not just a slogan with him. But with
that said, he is willing to be convinced
when the facts of an issue that he
doesn't fully understand are put before
him. That is exactly what our guest
today has done.
Dr. Peter Kuznick is a professor of
history at American University here in
Washington, D.C. And he's the founder
and director of the award-winning
Nuclear Studies Institute. He's the
author of many books including The
Untold History of the United States,
which along with writer, director, and
producer Oliver Stone, he turned into a
10-part Showtime series. He's also a
lifelong activist in support of peace
and human rights. Peter, thanks so much
for joining us. It's always great to
have you.
>> Always good to be with you, John.
Thank you.
>> Well, there are about a dozen different
places to begin, but I think I'd like to
start with your most recent interview
because you covered so many critically
important issues in it. You and Oliver
Stone appeared on the Tucker Carlson
show to discuss US relations with Russia
or the lack of US relations with Russia.
You spoke about the war in Ukraine. You
spoke about prospects for nuclear
confrontation. So, I'd like to begin
with that. I'm going to ask you the same
question that Tucker Carlson asked you.
How close do you think we are to nuclear
war?
>> I guess that depends which day you ask
me that question.
We were on with Tucker
back in, I guess, December.
And then he didn't play it for 4 weeks.
And by then the world had changed a
little bit.
I mean,
>> [clears throat]
>> and I and I say that because
under Biden
I was scared shitless, really. And I was
very, very worried under Biden. Not
because Biden wanted a nuclear war or
anybody sane wants a nuclear war. There
are have been, as we could discuss, some
some people in positions of authority
who have wanted a nuclear war over the
years.
Uh and
and even now
I So somebody like Keith Payne
who
headed the writing of the nuclear
posture review during Trump's first term
back in the '80s Keith Payne was writing
that we could fight and win a nuclear
war. We'd probably lose 20 million
people, but it might be worth it to
eliminate communism, the Soviet Union.
And so now he's still there and he's
still influencing Trump. Or at least he
was during the first term.
So there are people out there who are
pathological
insane and do welcome a nuclear war. But
that's not Biden, that's not Putin, and
it's not Xi or any of the other people
in charge of the nuclear arsenals now.
But under Biden, what got me so worried
is each time Ukraine wanted a new weapon
system Biden's immediate response was
no, we can't do that cuz it'd be too
dangerous a provocation.
It would cross Russia's red lines and
for either potentially force an
increased Russian response or the
possible use of tactical nuclear
weapons. And so Biden would would refuse
it. The pressure on him would increase
and he'd always cave in. Much like Obama
would always cave in to the pressure.
Biden caved into the pressure, whether
it was the F-16s or the HIMARS or the
ATACMS each time, you know, and the
thing about throwing red lines like
Putin has done
is that you can do it once and ignore
the provocation. Maybe you could do it
twice and ignore the provocation. But
you know, if you repeatedly draw red
lines and don't act when they're
crossed, then you lose all credibility
at home and internationally. And the
Americans were banking on the idea that
we had pushed them pushed the red line
time and again and Putin had not acted,
so we had could do anything we wanted
and Putin would not act. When you're
dealing with a nuclear armed world, you
can't play that kind of game of chicken.
And that's what the US was doing under
Biden. But I knew and I said it on
Tucker Carlson, for example, that Putin
had shown restraint.
And that was partly because he knew that
the new administration was coming in
and that he had a friendlier relation
with Trump and that Trump was more
appreciative not of the dangers of
escalation and had warned about the
threat of nuclear war, but also about
that he that he was hoping for a better
relation, a reset with Russia. He said,
of course, you know, why shouldn't we be
friends with Russia? It'd be in
everybody's interest.
So, when Putin came when Trump came in,
I was hopeful that we were a little less
close to nuclear war than we had been
under Biden.
However, Trump's early
actions and statements
have undermined my hope that we are
actually moving in the right direction.
Trump, you know, and and again, my
people I I deal with who like Trump
always say, "Well, take what Trump says
seriously, but don't take him
literally."
You know, and I I I try to
exercise that that
you know, rationality when when in
dealing with with Trump because
you know, the things that come out of
his mouth are so absurd often and so
little connection to reality because
he's a mafia boss. He's a liar. He He
boasts, you know, he's a bully, you
know, and and he's not a normal
statesman, politician, certainly not a
normal president, I don't think a normal
human being.
So,
so you know,
I have to try to restrain myself, but
the threats he's making already to Putin
you know, not only saying of course
peace would be in Russia's interest
which it's in everybody's interest to
end this damn war. It should never have
started. And you know, we could have so
easily been avoided if we had any real
statesmanship or leadership. But at this
point when he's making threats to Russia
as if his bullying mafia tactics are
going to work with Putin you know, the
world is different now. It is a
different world, even a different world
in 2017.
We've got this new these new and much
stronger alliances
between Russia and China Russia and
North Korea, even Russia and Iran,
although it's not a military alliance. I
mean that that the old game plan does
not work and and it doesn't work with
Russia, this kind of threatening and
bullying saying that if Russia doesn't
agree to a
settlement on the terms that Trump
wants, we're going to increase the
sanctions, give more arms to Ukraine,
and Putin's going to pay the price. That
is not going to work. You know, so
we always say that Trump is
transactional, that he wants to cut
deals, that he wants but but it's not
from the standpoint the Chinese like to
talk about win-win diplomacy. I like the
idea. It's the old Henry Wallace
concept,
>> [snorts]
>> Franklin Roosevelt concept of diplomacy.
The The American approach has always
been zero-sum game. We win and you lose.
And that is much more Trump's mentality.
And so when he talks about making
cutting deals or having friendly
relationships,
I was on Chinese TV a couple nights ago.
And it was interesting because we were
talking about US-China policy. And of
the four guests on this Chinese TV show,
I was the only one who held out even a
modicum of hope that relations with
China can improve under Trump. The other
three guests, two of whom were in in
China,
had no hope at all.
And as one of the the guests said that
Trump has two ways of dealing of
approaching other countries. Uh either
they're enemies or they're vassals. You
know, it's not as if he can deal with
other people as equals, but he admires
strong people. He admires autocrats.
>> Yes.
>> Xi Jinping, Putin. So I I I'm hopeful
that the transactional side of him uh
could
be willing to find mutually beneficial
resolutions.
But you know, even Tucker expressed
openly
his fear of what Trump is doing. That
Trump's surrounding himself with all
these neoconservatives.
>> Yes, yes.
>> You you look at his
his nominees and his appointees.
And there's almost nobody who's got a
peaceful diplomatic win-win approach to
the world. They're the worst of the
neocons.
>> They really are.
>> I mean this but this whole
administration, there was that popular
term in the 19th century of a
cacastocracy.
Government by the [clears throat] worst
people.
>> That's right.
>> And which was the case in the late 19th
century and it's the case again. I mean
the only thing that these people he's
put in there can do is blow up the
government, make government
non-functioning, make it a punitive
weapon to a cudgel to beat people down,
uh and and to dismantle the federal
government. Linda McMahon in charge of
education?
I mean, not only is she a fool, but she
also doesn't believe in public
education. You see, so these people can
dismantle these agencies, but I think
that Trump's base is in for a very, very
rough time, as all Americans are going
to be.
>> Peter, uh I want to ask you a question
about recent history. As you know, I
spent many years at the CIA. I was a
Middle East specialist, not a Russia
specialist, but one thing that always
struck me about my colleagues who were
working on Russia after the fall of the
Soviet Union
was that their marching orders were not
to change CIA policy at all. Russia was
seen as the same enemy that it always
had been as the Soviet Union during Cold
War. And except for this very brief
period during the presidency of Boris
Yeltsin, this is in the late 1990s, US
foreign policy didn't change at all
toward Russia.
Why did relations not improve between
the US and Russia when the Soviet Union
fell apart?
>> Well, uh
the morning the afternoon that Oliver
and I were on Tucker Carlson,
he interviewed my friend Jeff Sachs in
the morning.
And in Untold History, Oliver and I took
Jeff Sachs
personally to task because
you know, he's been identified as the
person who headed the Harvard team who
was brought in by Yeltsin
to reform the Russian economy after the
collapse of the Soviet Union.
To put effectively through shock
therapy.
And after Untold History came out, Jeff
emailed me and he said, "Peter, you guys
really raked me over the coals in untold
history."
He said, "I understand that, but it's
not wasn't fair." Uh and he went on to
this lengthy defense of himself.
And he said that the Russians rejected
his advice over and over again, that he
wasn't responsible for the shock
therapy. Cuz we know that
the life expectancy in Russia dropped
from 67 for 66 down to 57.
They were impoverished. The economy
shrunk to the size of the Netherlands.
Poverty was rampant. I mean, they
overnight they some a lot of the people
they had what they called gangster
capitalism. And some people were able to
get rich overnight, but the overall
majority of Russians were devastated
during the 1990s, the Yeltsin period.
So, the US seeing that Russia was so
weakened,
H. W. Bush and and
and uh Clinton, uh they could be very
on one hand they could be very
have a certain largesse toward Russia,
but on the other hand they were
privately gloating over the fact that
the former US adversary throughout the
Cold War
uh was so weakened, devastated,
humiliated. And then in 1997,
when it looked like Yeltsin had no
chance of getting reelected, the US
moves in and the US provides this
support in the media and the and the
advisors and they get him narrowly
reelected in 1997.
But even when Putin came in,
he bent over backwards to be friendly
toward the United States.
I mean, he even talked about the Russia
joining NATO at one point or thinking
about it.
>> to ask you about that. He did ask about
the prospects of Russia joining NATO.
>> after 9/11, he was the first foreign
leader to get in touch with George W.
Bush to offer support, offer sympathy
for what happened to the United States.
And then he assisted us initially in the
invasion of Afghanistan. But what does
the US do? In 2002, we pull out of the
ABM Treaty, which was very important to
the Russians. Uh in 2003, we invade
Iraq, which the Russians were adamantly
opposed to. Uh and even before that, the
bombing in former Yugoslavia, which 95%
or more Russians thought was a war
crime. Uh
I mean, so the United States was the
hegemon. We were the unipolar power.
And we were going to act with impunity.
In 1990, when it looked like the Soviet
empire was collapsing,
uh Charles Krauthammer issued a
statement saying that this is America's
unipolar moment.
Uh nobody can resist us anywhere on the
planet. We are the total hegemonic
force. We can do what we want. And
nobody's going to be able to challenge
us for another 30 or 40 years.
And then the United States had that
decade. First, you have the Defense
Planning Guidance in '92 and '93, which
lays out explicitly this hegemonic
vision. And it was so stark that they
had to pull it back and say, "Oh no,
this is not our policy." And in 1997,
they formed the Project for New American
Century, which talks about total
American domination. This is Kristol and
Kagan's idea. And all the other neocons
signed on. It was the neocon Super Bowl.
They were in charge. They loved it. And
then they issued a report in 2000 saying
that
we have to dramatically increase our
military spending. However, we can't do
it overnight like we want to unless we
have a new Pearl Harbor.
Uh and they also that that that from the
beginning, they kept saying, "What we
have to do is finish what we started in
Iraq and we have to overthrow Saddam
Hussein." That was their game plan from
the beginning. And then they get their
new Pearl Harbor on 9/11 and they jump
into action immediately. And then in
2002, after we've invaded Afghanistan
and initially looked like we were
succeeding there, Crowdhammer revisits
his 1990 statement and said, "I was
wrong in 1990 about this being the
unipolar moment. It is actually the
unipolar era. It's not going to last 30
or 40 years, it's going to last
indefinitely, indefinitely into the
future. Nobody can challenge us anywhere
on the planet." In 2003, in 2002, in
2003, then they're feeling their oats,
they're so powerful
and they then January 5th, 2003, the New
York Times headlines in Sunday magazine
section, "American Empire, get used to
it."
>> Mhm.
>> You know, and they were they were
bragging they were bragging. They were
out front. All of the neocons were out
front about it and talking openly about
American Empire, the strongest empire
ever seen in the world. And but until
things unravel in Afghanistan and Iraq
and Amr Moussa, the head of the Arab
League, says that
the gates of hell are open in Iraq. And
it was. And they had no planning, they
had no idea what to do. They thought
they were going to be greeted as
liberators like Brezhnev thought they'd
be greeted as liberators in Afghanistan
would be over in a month and 10 years
later it's still going on. Well, it's
even worse in Afghanistan and Iraq. And
so they and Crowdhammer even in 2006
revisits his
buoyancy and says,
"Well, the apogee of American
unipolarity is over."
>> Yeah.
>> And but that doesn't stop them cuz in
2007,
at when Putin is at the NATO meeting,
the
they begin talking again openly about
expansion of NATO.
We enter the whole NATO expansion
because it was
you know, very, very reckless and stupid
and backfired or in some ways backfired.
And then in 2008, George W. Bush says we
want to put Ukraine and Georgia on fast
track into NATO. And that was
crossing a red line that Putin was not
willing to cross. And then we saw what
happened in Ukraine and we see the
position we're in now. So to get back to
your question about well, nuclear war
and the whole question of US-Russian
relations, I mean, it has been a mess
since 1917
when the US sent troops to join the
British and the French and the Japanese
and all the other European troops in
Russia to try to
curb the Russian Revolution. You know,
Wilson was not willing to go as far as
Churchill was in terms of actually
intervening to overthrow, defeat the
Bolsheviks. Wilson turned Churchill
down. Churchill said we need to strangle
Bolshevism in the cradle. And but that
was the idea that the Brits had. The
Americans were not quite willing to go
there, but they were furious with the
Soviets for pulling out of World War I
and they were more furious when the
Bolsheviks went into the Foreign
Ministry and showed all of the secret
treaties and agreements and deals that
the British and the French and the
Tsarist Russians had concluded for
dividing up the world after World War I
was over and we're living with the
effects of that in the Middle East, the
region that you know even even better.
So,
the Sykes-Picot stuff and
means So, when Russia pulls out, the the
West was furious because Russia was
providing the cannon fodder for a lot of
the fighting in World War I as they're
going to do again in World War II. So,
the US has not recognized Russia till 20
till 1933
when Roosevelt comes to office.
And then then when the
Germans invade the Soviet Union in 1941,
then Roosevelt figures out how to
provide lend-lease aid to the Soviet
Union. And they're our close ally in
fighting the Germans. And after they
turned back the German incursion into in
Moscow in late 1941,
uh
then in 1942, it's clear the US is
giving some material, some military aid,
and some some necessary armaments, and
the Russians are resisting, but Stalin
was making three demands.
One was for the same boundaries that
they had in in the Nazi-Soviet Pact,
which is mostly getting back what they
had lost after World War I.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh secondly, they wanted more more
material and military support, which the
US was way behind on its promises, but
the most important thing that they
wanted was a second front. What most
Americans don't know is that throughout
the war,
while the US and the Brits were
confronting 10 German divisions between
us, the Soviets were confronting more
than 200 German divisions,
which is why, you know, I ask my
students who won World War II, and if
they even know it that there was a World
War II and what side people were on,
they say the Americans won it. But the
Europeans say that the Brits and the
Brits won it, the Europeans won it.
According to the latest surveys that
I've read, 17% of the Europeans credit
the Soviets with playing a major role in
defeating Germany in World War II.
Churchill even admitted. He said the Red
Army tore the guts out of the German war
machine. And and if you look at American
coverage of so of World War II and the
Soviet role, the New York Times in 1942,
their articles saying that if we saved
the world from fascism, it's because of
the heroic Soviet sacrifice. We knew it.
And so then in May of '42, Roosevelt
writes to Stalin and he asked Stalin to
send over Foreign Minister Molotov and a
trusted general to Washington. He does.
They meet in in Washington, D.C. And
during that meeting, Roosevelt turns to
General Marshall, Chief of Staff
Marshall, and says, "Can we open up the
second front? Can we promise to open up
the second front before the end of this
year, before the end of 1942?" And
Marshall says, "Absolutely." He and
Eisenhower had already drawn up plans
for the US invasion in Western Europe.
However,
uh
Churchill sabotaged it.
He had some good reasons and a lot of
bad reasons. Uh from the Russian
standpoint, it looked like they wanted
the Soviets to be bled white uh and to
suffer and to be weakened and defeated
like many Americans might want to see
today. Uh
and so the Soviets
largely, not single-handedly cuz they
had support and help, but they played
the key role in driving back the
Germans. They defeated them at
Stalingrad. They finally overcome the
horrific Blitzkrieg in Leningrad in
which
Putin's father was badly wounded.
Putin's younger brother died during that
siege as did maybe a million people in
Leningrad, in the siege of Leningrad,
when they were eating the wallpaper, you
know, the glue off the wallpaper, try
and make soup out of that. They were
desperate beyond belief. Uh and so and
that's what the that's the history that
the Russians know. The Americans have
never had that kind of history and that
kind of knowledge. And then the but the
other key turning point that Americans
have no clue about was Roosevelt chose
Henry Wallace as vice president in 1940
because Wallace was the leading
anti-fascist
uh in the New Deal administration.
>> That's right.
>> He was the leading visionary as
secretary of agriculture, which was key
to the New Deal recovery. And hated
fascism, was an anti-racist, exemplary.
And Roosevelt knew in 1940 that we were
gearing up for a war against fascism, uh
Japanese militarism and imperialism and
and German fascism. And he wanted a real
anti-fascist on the ticket as vice
president. But the Democratic Party did
not want to put
Wallace on.
>> Mhm.
>> Partly because Wallace comes from a
Republican farm family. His father had
been secretary of agriculture under
Harding and Coolidge. His grandfather
was mooted as secretary of agriculture
back in the 19th century. And so Wallace
comes from Iowa and
party bosses didn't trust him cuz he
didn't become officially a Democrat
until into the 1930s. But Wallace was
also too radical.
And so
they refused to put him on the ticket.
And Roosevelt writes this extraordinary
letter to the Democratic Party
Convention in 1940 saying, "We already
have a conservative Wall Street
finance-dominated party, the
Republicans. If the Democrats aren't
going to be a progressive liberal party
fighting for social justice, then the
Democrats have no reason to exist and
I'm not going to run as a candidate on
that ticket." He He said wrote a letter
he was going to deliver turning down the
nomination in 1940.
>> Wow.
>> But before he did that, Eleanor
Roosevelt went to the convention, the
first time a first lady had been there,
and made clear to them that he was
serious and he was going to withdraw his
candidate if they didn't put Wallace on
his vice president. So, they
begrudgingly did that in 1940. And as
vice president, Wallace, after Henry
Luce writes his editorials and speeches
that the 20th century must be the
American century, that the US is going
to dominate the world in every way,
financially, militarily, culturally,
intellectually, Wallace refutes that and
says, "No, the 20th century must be the
century of the common man." He says, "We
need a worldwide people's revolution in
the tradition of the American
Revolution, the French Revolution, the
German Revolutions of 1848, Latin
American Revolutions, and the Russian
Revolution." And he calls for an end to
imperialism, an end to colonialism,
spreading the fruits of science and
technology all over the world.
I mean, this is the vision that Wallace
had. And
so, the party bosses decide they have to
oust Wallace in '44. Get him off the
ticket. They know that Roosevelt is
sick, and he's not able to run another
campaign, and he's never going to
survive another 4 years in the
presidency. So, whoever is vice
president is become the next president.
And they know that Wallace is this
visionary who understands a better
world, wants to work with the Soviets to
create that better world. And this he
was the person who the Soviets trusted,
he and Roosevelt were the ones they
trusted. But, the party bosses said,
"Well, we need to find an alternative."
And they chose Harry Truman. Not because
he was smart enough, not because he was
worldly enough, not because he was
knowledgeable enough, but because he
didn't have any real enemies.
Now, Truman, I mean, I don't know if you
want me to go into any of this.
>> I I want to I want to add something. I
want to add something real quickly. When
you and I first met, I had just watched
this episode of
of The Untold History of the United
States. I was always a fan of Henry
Wallace. I did not know the details of
what in my mind was a coup against
Wallace at the 1944 Democratic National
Convention until I saw your show.
This is to me one of the most
fascinating episodes in recent American
history and it changed the course of the
world.
>> It did. I mean,
you know, Wallace was
just I'll do a quick version. Yeah. You
know, July 20th, 1944, the day the
Democratic Party convention began in
Chicago, Gallup released a poll of
potential voters asking them who they
wanted on the ticket as vice president.
65% said they wanted Wallace back as
vice president. He was the second most
popular man in America behind Roosevelt.
2% said they wanted Harry Truman as vice
president. Unless I did the math, 65 is
bigger than two. But we weren't a
democracy and the Democratic Party is
not not a democracy. And so,
uh
the party bosses had the whole thing
cooked for Truman beforehand. But the
first night of the convention, Wallace
makes a seconding speech for Roosevelt
and the place goes wild. There's a
spontaneous demonstration led by among
others Adlai Stevenson and Hubert
Humphrey and it goes on for an hour. In
the middle of it, Claude Pepper, who's
then the senator from Florida, realized
that if he could get to the podium and
get Wallace's name in nomination,
Wallace would sweep the convention, defy
the bosses, be back on the ticket as
vice president. Uh and so he fights his
way through the crowd. The party bosses
led by Chicago Mayor Frank Kelly see
what's happening. They start rushing to
the podium. Sam Jackson was chairing the
session. Uh Sam Jackson later said he
had orders not to let Wallace get
nominated. Kelly starts screaming, "It's
a fire hazard. I adjourn this
immediately." And Jackson says, "I have
a motion to adjourn. All in favor say I.
Maybe 5% say I. All opposed, nay.
Everybody yells out nay. He says, motion
adjourned. The eyes have it.
At that point, Pepper was 5 ft from the
microphone. Had Pepper gotten 5 more
feet to the microphone, he'd get Wallace
the Democratic nomination, there would
have been no atomic bombings in World
War II, possibly and likely no Cold War
because Wallace had a whole different
vision. But Wallace agreed to stay on as
Secretary of Commerce.
And from that position, he fought for
the next year and a half against Truman
and the Cold War and the arms nuclear
arms race until finally he's the last
new dealer left, the last one who's got
a vision for peace, the last one who
wants to get along with the Soviets and
make the world a better world, the last
one who embraced that vision that that
Roosevelt expressed in '42. Roosevelt
also said in '42 that what we need now
is four policemen. We need China to
police Asia,
Russia to police that region.
He said Britain to police Europe and the
United States to police the rest of the
world. And these four policemen can
bring peace and stability to the
post-war world.
Truman's vision was very, very
different. Truman did not like the
Soviets. He did not trust the Soviets.
Truman was a little man. And Truman
would was like Trump in some ways. Like
Trump, people tell me Trump listens to
the last person in the room. And Truman
would always do that. And Wallace could
convince him. And and Truman would say,
oh, I don't mind, you know,
Stalin reminds me of Boss Pendergast in
Kansas City. I can deal with him. We'll
get along with them. But then he goes
and he listens to his hardliners. And
Wallace was fighting a lonely fight in
1945 and 1946.
And so we have that whole horrible
history of the Cold War
in which we're lucky to have survived.
And as you know very well, there were
several times in which it looked like we
weren't going to survive. We came very
close to nuclear war either by accident
or by stupid policies and during the
Cuban Missile Crisis and many times
afterwards when we would get false
intelligence that there was an incoming
missile attack on the United States or
they would get false intelligence
through computer failures or satellite
failures there was an incoming missile
attack against the Soviet Union. And but
since we didn't have AI in the loop for
nuclear deployment, we had human beings
who were hesitant to respond the way
they were supposed to respond and they
didn't give the order to launch. But we
came very close on numerous occasions
including 1989, 1995
on both sides. And and so
you know, I guess the long-winded answer
to your question about why US Soviet and
then US Russian relations have been so
bad
and that's partly because the US
approach was based on this idea of
American exceptionalism or American
unipolarity or America is the
indispensable nation or America is the
hegemon or now America is the bully
and we were going to impose our will and
dominate the world. Let me take it back
to a very crucial memo which most 99.9%
of Americans never read or heard of and
that was George Kennan the architect of
the Cold War wrote a secret memo in 1990
actually 1948 48 in which he says we
have 6.3%
of the world's population yet we control
50% of the world's wealth.
The challenge ahead of us is to maintain
this position of disparity.
We're not going to do that with
ideological slogans. He said, "We can't
help to be the envy of the object of
envy and resentment."
>> Mhm.
>> And we're not going to maintain this
position by idealistic slogans and
freedom and democracy and human rights,
but by dealing with cold, hard power
concepts.
>> That's right.
>> And that's what the Cold War was about.
And that's, you know, in in the
nightmares of the Cold War, the worst of
which, of course, was the US invasion of
Vietnam.
>> That's right.
>> Uh
you know, and we like to see ourselves,
the idea that I grew up with and you
grew up with, that America was different
from all other countries.
That America was better. That all other
countries were motivated by wanting
land or want or by greed or geopolitics,
but the US only wanted to spread freedom
and democracy.
>> Mhm.
>> I grew up with that. You know, and it
took took, in some ways, Vietnam to
knock that out of me. And you know, it
was the air we breathed growing up in
the '50s, '60s, and '70s. By the '70s,
people were not believing it. Uh but
this is what American policy makers act
on, the idea of impunity.
As Madeleine Albright said, uh
you know, if we use force, it's because
we're the United States of America.
We're the indispensable nation. We stand
taller and see farther into the future
than other countries.
And and uh Hillary Clinton echoed that.
Obama echoed that. This idea that we're
the indispensable nation. Well, the
world has passed us by in a lot of ways.
And, you know, Trump now threatening
100% tariffs on the BRICS nations if
they try to replace the dollar. You
know, that I mean, the stuff that's go
that's being said and done is so stupid,
so parochial, so out of touch with
reality in the world, that I'm afraid
that if Trump acts on some of his
threats, that we're back in the position
of threatening World War III and
creating a world in which the US is
increasingly isolated with some European
allies.
You know, because even question I guess
raised all the time about why didn't the
global South go along with the sanctions
against Russia?
>> Right.
>> And I think that
you know, with the global South was the
saw the hypocrisy. They saw all the
years of US invasions over and over and
over again. US intervention, US
overthrowing foreign governments and
foreign leaders who opposed US policy,
even if they were popularly elected,
democratically elected, even if they had
the support like Mosaddegh. The US
ambassador in Iran in '53 wrote back
that Mosaddegh has the support of
between 95 and 98% of the Iranian
people. We gave a right? And so we
over the CIA overthrows him anyway.
>> Yep.
>> You know, and the same thing in in
Guatemala uh with Arbenz, you know,
Allende, we in over and over again. And
and so uh
the London Economist wrote a few years
ago that to Biden and the US, this looks
like a fight between uh
autocracy and democracy. Remember Biden
kept saying that. He's but the London
Economist said to the rest of the world,
it looks like a fight between autocracy
and hypocrisy. And that's why they
refused to go along.
>> That's right.
>> Jimmy Carter recently passed.
>> Yes.
>> and
you know, Oliver and I were really hard
on Jimmy Carter.
>> Yes.
>> Uh because he came to office with
idealistic vision. Uh but was a product
of the Trilateral Commission. It was
handpicked by David Rockefeller and
Zbigniew Brzezinski.
>> susceptible to Brzezinski's constant
propagandization.
>> Uh uh and Brzezinski, I mean, you know,
given your CIA background that the CIA
always gave the president's daily
briefs.
>> Yes.
>> But Carter appointed Brzezinski national
security advisor.
And Brzezinski insisted from day one
giving the
president briefing by himself with
nobody from the CIA present and nobody
else present.
And in his memoir, Brzezinski is open
about it. He said that after a period of
time, I heard my words coming out of
Carter's mouth.
He said, "I was shocked by the extent to
which he was repeating and thinking in
terms of the ways that I had implanted
in his head." And and the Carter
presidency, which in some ways, you
know, we just had Trump's
monosyllabic
moronic, boring inaugural address. I was
actually on CBS, you know, and and and
what I said was that this is the worst,
most visionless inaugural address I've
ever heard or read. And I've read them
all going back to
1793, George Washington's inaugural
address was 135 words long. Right? But
we know them all and they mostly have
soaring visions. I said this was either
the product of a diminished mind or
diminished oratorical skills. It was
embarrassing how how mundane, stupid,
prosaic, boring, visionless this
inaugural address was. As well as
self-contradictory, as we can talk
about. Um but Jimmy Carter, I saw that
But I But Oliver and I said he was a
failed president, but was a wonderful
example, a moral paragon as an
ex-president. You know, the best
ex-president we've ever had.
>> Best one.
>> And Jimmy Carter said in 2019, he was
addressing the congregation in his
church in Plains. And he said, "I was on
the phone last night with Donald Trump.
And Trump was expressing his deep
concerns about China."
And Carter said, "I I them I don't fear
the Chinese century, I welcome it. He
said, "Do you know how many times
China's been at war since 1979?
Zero."
>> Zero.
>> And he said, "While our country has been
constantly at war." He said, "Since the
founding" this was 2019 he said, "in the
242 year history of the United States,
we've only had 16 years of peace."
Uh he said that we're the uh
biggest the most he said, "We're the
most
in the history of the world." While
we've been fighting wars, spending
trillions of dollars on these wars, the
the Chinese have invested in high-speed
railway and infrastructure. He said,
"They've got 18,000 square 18,000 miles
of high-speed railway. We've got zero."
He said, "Our bridges are collapsing,
our roads are collapsing, our schools
are collapsing. If we had put that money
instead of into these wars, constant
wars, endless wars, forever wars, the
country would be so much richer, the
people would be so much happier." He had
that vision, you know, but Trump doesn't
have that vision.
You know, the best I can hope for with
Trump is a kind of transactionality,
that he'll see that it's more in
America's interest to support peaceful
resolution than not, but I you know, but
and I was hopeful. And Oliver and I were
hopeful on Tucker's show, and Tucker was
hopeful. Uh but then you see who Trump
appointed, and you see the things
they've been saying, and you listen to
Marco Rubio's testimony, you know, and
this was a warmonger testimony. Yeah,
he's he's
>> longtime foreign policy hawk. You know,
and before I let you go, I want to I
want to encourage everybody who's
watching watching this to go to YouTube
and to type in